Dismount!
Herman's horse-sick!
Chaps, no one wander off!
Some of the passageways in here can run for miles.
I don't think this is such a good idea.
What is it?
Alfred, did you get anything yet?
Nothing.
The kid's got something.
I got something, Fedora!  I got something right here.
Oh, look at that!
- We're rich!  We're rich!   - Shut up!
Indy?
Indy?  What are they doing?
Indiana?  Indiana...?
We gotta find more stuff.
It's the Cross of Coronado.
Cort gave it to him in 1520.
I'll give that ring to my mama and put it on her bony finger!
That cross is an important artefact, it belongs in a museum.
Run back, tell Mr Havelock there are men looting in the caves.
Have him bring the sheriff. It's only a snake!
Did you hear me?
Right. Run back. Mr Havelock. The sheriff...
What are you gonna do?
I don't know. I'll think of something.
Dig with your hands, not your mouth!
- He's got our thing.  - Get him!
Mr Havelock!  Anybody!
Everybody's lost but me.
There he is!  Let's go!
Hey, you!  We're gonna get you!
Hey!  Come back here!
Come on!  Get him!
Come back here!
Here, let me!
Holy smoke!
Come on, kid.
There's no way out of this.
Toss up the whip!
You got heart, kid, but that belongs to me.
It belongs to Coronado.
Coronado is dead, and so are all of his grandchildren.
This should be in a museum.
Give me that!
A snake!
Don't let him get away!
Magic?
Make sure he doesn't double back.
OK, kid, out of the box, now!
Son of a bitch!
Damn!
Dad!
-Dad! It's important.  -Wait. Count to twenty.
- No, listen to me...  - Junior!
One, two, three, four...
In Greek.
May he who illuminated this illuminate me.
I brought the sheriff.
Just the man I want to see.
- Five or six of them...  - All right. You still got it?
Well, yes...  it's right here.
I'm glad to see that.
because the rightful owner of this cross
won't press charges if you give it back.
He's got witnesses, five or six of them.
Good day.
You lost today, kid.
But it doesn't mean you have to like it.
- Small world, Dr Jones.  - Too small for two of us.
I've had to reclaim my property from you before.
That belongs in a museum!
So do you!
Throw him over the side!
Grab him, he's getting away!
Archaeology is the search for fact...
...not truth.
If it's truth you're interested in, the philosophy class is down the hall.
Forget lost cities, exotic travel and digging up the world.
We don't follow maps to treasure, and "X" never ever marks the spot.
Seventy per cent of all archaeology is done in the library.
Research, reading...
We cannot afford to take mythology at face value.
Next week: Egyptology and the excavation of Naukratis of 1885.
I'll be in my office if anybody's got problems.
Marcus... I did it.
You've got it?
- Know how long I've looked for that?  - All your life.
- All my life.  - Well done, very well done indeed.
This will find a place of honour in our Spanish collection.
We can discuss my honorarium over dinner and champagne.
-Your treat. -Yes... my treat.
Dr Jones!
Your mail is on your desk. Here are your phone messages.
This is your schedule. These papers still need grading.
Irene, put everybody's name on a list...
...and I'll see each and every one of them in turn!
"Venice, Italy."
Dr Jones!  Dr Jones!
Dr Jones!
Dr Jones.
I trust your trip down was comfortable, Dr Jones.
My men didn't alarm you, I hope.
My name is Walter Donovan.
I know you. Your contributions to the museum have been generous.
Your collection is very impressive.
Like yourself, I have a passion for antiquities.
Have a look over here.
This might interest you.
Well, it's sandstone. Christian symbol.
Early Latin text. Mid-12th century.
- That was our assessment, too.  - Where's it from?
My engineers unearthed it north of Ankara, while excavating for copper.
Can you translate the inscription?
"'... who drinks the water I shall give him,' says the Lord,
"'will have a spring inside him welling up for eternal life.'
"Let them bring me to your Holy Mountain where you dwell,
"across the desert, through the mountain,
"to the Canyon of the Crescent Moon,
"to the temple where the cup that...
"...where the cup that holds the blood of Jesus Christ resides for ever."
The Holy Grail, Dr Jones.
The chalice used by Christ during the Last Supper,
that caught his blood at the Crucifixion
and was entrusted to Joseph of Arimathea.
The Arthur Legend. I've heard this bedtime story before.
Eternal life!  The gift of youth to whoever drinks from the Grail.
- That's a bedtime story I like!  - An old man's dream.
Every man's dream, including your father's, I believe.
Grail lore is his hobby.
He's the teacher of Medieval Literature the students hope they don't get.
You're neglecting your guests.
Along in a moment, dear.
Hard to resist, isn't it?  The Grail's final resting place described in detail.
What good is it?  This tablet speaks of deserts, mountains, canyons...
Pretty vague. Where do you start?
If the tablet were intact, but the top portion is missing.
Just the same, an attempt to recover the Grail is currently underway.
Let me tell you another bedtime story.
After the Grail was entrusted to Joseph, it was lost for a thousand years,
before it was found again by three brothers in the First Crusade.
I've heard this one, too.
Two of the brothers walked out of the desert 150 years later
and journeyed back to France, but only one made it.
Before dying of... extreme old age,
he supposedly imparted his tale to a Franciscan friar.
Not "supposedly", Dr Jones.
This is the manuscript in which the friar chronicled the knight's story.
It doesn't reveal the Grail's location,
but the knight promised that two markers would.
This tablet is one of those markers.
It proves the knight's story is true, but it's incomplete.
The second marker is in his dead brother's tomb.
Our project leader believes that tomb is located in Venice, Italy.
As you can now see, we're about to complete a great quest
that began almost two thousand years ago.
We're only one step away.
That's usually when the ground falls out from under you.
You could be more right than you know.
We've hit a snag.
Our project leader has vanished, along with all his research.
His colleague, Dr Schneider, has no idea of his whereabouts.
I want you to pick up the trail where he left off.
Find the man, and you will find the Grail.
You've got the wrong Jones, Mr Donovan.
- Why don't you try my father?  - We already have.
Your father is the man who's disappeared.
Your father and I have been friends for years,
and I've never seen you this concerned about him before.
Dad?
He's an academic, not a field man. Dad?
Dear God!
What's the old fool got himself into now?
I don't know, but whatever it is, he's in over his head.
It's today's mail, and it's been opened.
Mail...
That's it, Marcus.
"Venice, Italy."
What is it?
It's Dad's Grail diary.
Every clue he followed, every discovery he made.
A complete record of his search for the Holy Grail.
This is his whole life. Why would he have sent this to me?
I don't know... but someone must want it pretty badly.
Do you believe, Marcus?
Do you believe the Grail actually exists?
The search for it is the search for the divine in all of us.
But if you want facts, I've none to give you.
At my age, I'm prepared to take a few things on faith.
Call Donovan, tell him I'll take that ticket to Venice now.
I'll tell him we'll take two.
- What'll happen in Ven...?  - Dr Schneider will meet you.
My apartment in Venice is at your disposal.
Thank you.
Dr Jones... good luck.
Be very careful. Don't trust anybody.
Ah, Venice.
How will we recognise Dr Schneider?
I don't know. Maybe he'll know us.
Dr Jones?
Yes.
I knew it was you. You have your father's eyes.
And my mother's ears, but the rest is yours.
It looks like the best parts are spoken for.
- Marcus Brody?  - That's right.
- Dr Elsa Schneider.  - How do you do?
I last saw your father in the library.
He was very close to tracking down the tomb. He was so excited.
- He was as giddy as a schoolboy.  - Attila the Professor?
He was never giddy, even as a schoolboy.
- Frlein, will you permit me?  - I usually don't.
- Me neither. - Then I permit you.
- But by tomorrow it will have faded.  - Tomorrow I'll...
- I hate to interrupt, but the reason...  - I have something to show you.
Your father sent me to get an ancient plan of the city.
When I got back, he'd gone, with all his papers except that scrap.
- Roman numerals.  - Here is the library.
- That doesn't look like a library.  - Looks like a converted church.
It's the literal truth. You're on holy ground.
These columns were brought back as spoils of war,
after the sacking of Byzantium in the Crusades.
The library's closing soon. I'll arrange for us to stay a little longer.
Marcus, I've seen this window before.
- Where?  - Right here. In Dad's diary.
- You see?  - Look, Indy. The Roman numerals.
- Dad was onto something here.  - But we don't know what they mean.
He sent me the diary for a reason. Let's keep it to ourselves.
- Find something?  - Three, seven and ten.
- The numerals are on the window.  - I must be blind.
He wasn't looking for a book about the tomb, but for the tomb itself.
The tomb is in the library. You said it used to be a church. Look!
Three.
Seven. Seven.
Ten... and ten.
Where's the ten?
Look around for the ten.
Three and seven...
Three and seven and ten...
Ten!  "X" marks the spot.
- Bingo!  - You don't disappoint, Dr Jones.
- You're just like your father.  - Except he's lost and I'm not.
Lower me down.
Look after this for me, will you?
Come on!
- Pagan symbols, 4th or 5th century.  - Right.
Six hundred years before the Crusades.
The Christians dug their own passages centuries later.
If there's a knight of the First Crusade here, that's where we'll find him.
- What's this one?  - The Ark of the Covenant.
- Are you sure?  - Pretty sure.
Watch out.
It's petroleum. I should sink a well down here and retire!
The lighter.
Oh, rats...!
Come on.
Come here.
Look, it must be one of these.
Look at the artistry of these carvings and the scrollwork.
It's this one.
This is it. We've found it!
Look!
The engraving on the shield is the same as on the Grail tablet.
The shield is the second marker!
What's that?
It's a rubbing Dad made of the Grail tablet.
Just like your father, giddy as a schoolboy!
Wouldn't it be wonderful if he were here to see this?
He'd never have made it past the rats. He hates rats.
Get back against the wall!
Quick, under it!  Air pocket!
- Don't wander off.  - What? What?!
I think I've found a way out. Deep breath!
Ah... Venice!
- Are you crazy?  Not between them!  - Between them?  Are you crazy?
- I said go around!  - You said between them!
I said don't go between them!
No!
- Why kill us?   - Because you're looking for the Grail.
- Did you kill my father, too?  - No!
Where is he?
Talk or you're dead!  Dammit, tell me!  Tell me!
- If you don't let go, we'll both die!  - Then we'll die!
My soul is prepared. How's yours?
- This is your last chance!  - No, Dr Jones, it's yours.
All right, where's my father?
If you let me go, I will tell you.
- Who are you?  - My name is Kazim.
Why did you try to kill me?
The secret of the Grail has been safe for a thousand years.
All that time, the Brotherhood of the Cruciform Sword
have been prepared to do anything to keep it safe.
Let me off at this jetty.
Ask yourself, why do you seek the Cup of Christ?
Is it for His glory... or for yours?
I didn't come for the Cup of Christ, I came to find my father.
In that case, God be with you.
He's held in the Castle of Brunwald on the Austrian-German border.
- How's the head?  - Better, now I've seen this.
It's the name of a city: Alexandretta.
The knights of the First Crusade laid siege to Alexandretta.
The entire city was destroyed.
The present city of Iskenderun is built on its ruins.
Remember what the Grail tablet said?  "Across the desert,
"through the mountain, to the Canyon of the Crescent Moon."
- Where, exactly?  - Your father would know.
Your father did know!  Look, he made a map!
He pieced it together from clues in the Grail quest.
A map with no names. A city with an oasis due east... here.
He knew the course turns south to the mountains, straight to the canyon!
He knew everything except where to begin: the name of the city.
- Alexandretta. Now we know. - Yes, now we know.
Tell Sallah to meet you in Iskenderun.
What about you?
I'm going after Dad.
Elsa?
- My room! - Mine, too.
- What were they looking for?  - This.
The Grail diary.
You had it?
- You didn't trust me.  - I didn't know you.
At least I let you tag along.
Yes, give them a flower and they'll follow you anywhere.
- Knock it off. You're not mad.  - No?
No. You like the way I do things.
Lucky I don't do things the same way or you'd still be standing at the pier!
What's going on there?
I've nearly been incinerated, drowned and chopped into fish bait.
We're caught in something sinister here, and my Dad found out more than is looking for.
Until I'm sure, I'll do things the way I think they should be done.
How dare you kiss me!
Leave me alone. I don't like fast women.
And I hate arrogant men.
I love Venice...
What do you know about this place?
I know the Brunwalds are art collectors.
What are you going to do?
I don't know. I'll think of something.
- Yes?  - Not before time.
Did you intend to leave us standing on the doorstep?
We're drenched.
I've gone and caught a sniffle.
Are you expected?
Do not take that tone with me.
Tell the Baron that Lord Clarence MacDonald and his assistant
are here to view the tapestries.
- Tapestries?  - The man is dense...!
This is a castle, isn't it?  There are tapestries?
This is a castle. And we have many tapestries.
And if you are a Scottish lord, then I am Mickey Mouse!
How dare he?
Nazis. I hate these guys.
- I think he's in here.  - How do you know?
Because it's wired.
Indy?  Indy!
Don't worry, this is kid's play. I'll be right back.
Junior?
- Yes, sir.  - It is you, Junior.
Don't call me that, please.
- What are you doing here?  - I came to get you...
Late 14th century, Ming Dynasty. It breaks the heart.
And the head!  You hit me.
I'll never forgive myself.
Don't worry, I'm fine.
Thank God.
It's a fake!
You can tell by the cross-section.
No!
We've got to get out of here.
Sorry about your head. I thought you were one of them.
Dad, they come in through the doors!
Good point. But better safe than sorry.
I was wrong this time, but not when I mailed you my diary.
You obviously got it.
I got it and I used it. We found the entrance to the catacombs.
- Through the library?  - Right.
I knew it.
And the tomb of Sir Richard?
Found it.
He was actually there?
- You saw him?  - What was left of him.
And his shield?
The inscription on Sir Richard's shield?
- Alexandretta.  - Alexandretta!  Of course!
On the pilgrim trail from the Eastern Empire.
Junior, you did it!
No, Dad, you did. Forty years.
- If only I could have been with you.  - There were rats, Dad.
- Rats?  - Yeah. Big ones.
- What do the Nazis want with you?  - They wanted my diary.
I had to get that book as far away from me as I could.
Yeah
Dr Jones.
- Yes?  - Yes?
I will take the book now.
- What book?  - You have the diary in your pocket.
You dolt!
You think my son would be that stupid, bringing my diary back here?
You didn't, did you?
You didn't bring it, did you?
- You did!  - Can we discuss this later?
- I mailed it to the Marx Brothers!  - Take it easy!
Take it easy?  I sent it home so it wouldn't fall into their hands!
- I came here to save you!  - Oh, yeah?
- Who's going to save you, Junior?  - I told you...
...don't call me Junior.
Look what you did!
I can't believe what you...
Elsa?
That's far enough. Put down the gun or the Frlein dies.
She's one of them. She's a Nazi.
- What?  - Trust me.
- I will kill her.  - Go ahead.
- Don't shoot!  - Don't worry, he won't.
- Indy, please, do what he says!  - Don't listen to her.
Enough. She dies!
Wait!
I'm sorry.
No. Don't be.
But you should have listened to your father.
She ransacked her own room, and I fell for it.
How did you know she was a Nazi?
She talks in her sleep.
I didn't trust her. Why did you?
Because he didn't take my advice.
Donovan.
Didn't I warn you not to trust anybody, Dr Jones?
I misjudged you, Walter.
I knew you'd sell your mother,
but not your country and your soul to the slime of humanity.
Dr Schneider, there are pages torn out of this.
This book contained a map, a map with no names.
Directions from the unknown city to the secret canyon.
- So it did.  - Where are these missing pages?
You're wasting your breath. He won't tell us. He doesn't have to.
It's obvious where the pages are. He's given them to Marcus Brody.
Marcus?  You dragged him along?  He's not up to the challenge.
He sticks out. We'll find him.
The hell you will. He's got a two-day head start on you.
Brody's got friends all over, he speaks a dozen languages,
he'll blend in, disappear. You'll never see him again.
With any luck, he's got the Grail already.
Does anyone speak English? Ancient Greek?
Water?  No, fish make love in it.
Thank you so much. No, I really don't want... Thank you.
No, I'm a vegetarian.
Does anyone understand a word I'm saying?
- Mr Brody!  - What a relief.
Marcus Brody, sir!
- Where's Indy?  - In Austria. A slight detour.
- You're alone?  - Yes, but everything's under control.
- You've arranged supplies?  - Yes. But where are we going?
This map will show you. It was drawn by...
Mr Brody. Welcome to Iskenderun.
The museum director has sent a car for you.
- Well... Your servant, sir.  - And I am his.
Follow me, please.
- My reputation precedes me.  - There is no museum.
- Papers, please!  - Papers?  Of course.
- Run. - Yes.
Papers?  Got it here. Just finished reading it.
- Egyptian Mail, morning edition. Run!  - Did you say...?
Run!
Up here, up here, quick!  Find the back door!
Intolerable.
Dr Schneider, you must return to Berlin at once.
A rally at the Institute of Aryan Culture.
Your presence is requested at the highest level.
Thank you. I'll meet you at Iskenderun.
Take this diary to the Reichsmuseum and show them our progress.
Without the map, it's useless.
- Let me kill them now. - No.
If we don't find the pages, we'll need them alive.
Always do what the doctor orders.
Don't look at me like that. We both wanted the Grail.
I would have done anything to get it. You would have, too.
I'm sorry you think so.
I can't forget how wonderful it was.
Thank you. It was rather wonderful.
Dr Schneider. Your car is waiting.
That's how Austrians say goodbye.
And this is how we say goodbye in Germany, Dr Jones.
- I like the Austrian way better. - So did I.
Get the ropes loose. We gotta get to Marcus before the Nazis.
You said he had two days' start, that he'd blend in.
Are you kidding?  I made that up. He got lost once in his own museum!
Can you reach my left jacket pocket?
- What am I looking for?  - My lucky charm.
Feels like a cigarette lighter.
Burn through the ropes.
Very good.
- I ought to tell you something.  - Don't get sentimental now.
The floor's on fire. See?
- And the chair.  - Move!  Move!
- Approaching the table.  - Move!
We have Marcus Brody.
And more important, we have the map!
"By command of the Frer. Secrecy essential to success.
"Eliminate the American conspirators."
Germany has declared war on the Jones boys!
- Dad?  - What?
Head for the fireplace!
I think I can get these ropes off. Whoops!
- Our situation has not improved.  - Listen, I'm almost free.
This is intolerable!
- I'm out, Dad.  - Well done, boy!
Come on, Dad.
Dead end.
There's got to be a secret door or... a passageway.
I find that if I just sit down and think...
...the solution presents itself.
Great!  More boats!
This has been just another typical day for you, eh?
No!  It's been better than most.
Come on, Dad!
What?  We're not going on the boat?
Stop!  Stop!
You're going the wrong way. We have to get to Berlin.
- Brody's this way. - My diary's in Berlin.
We don't need the diary, Marcus has the map.
There is more in the diary than just the map.
All right, Dad. Tell me.
Well, he who finds the Grail must face the final challenge.
- What final challenge?  - Three devices of lethal cunning.
- Booby traps?  - Oh, yes!
But I found the clues to safely take us through
in the Chronicles of St Anselm!
Well, what are they?
Can't you remember?
I wrote them in my diary so I wouldn't have to remember!
Half the German army's after us and you want to go to Berlin?!
Yes. All that matters is the Grail.
- What about Marcus?  - Marcus would agree with me.
Two selfless martyrs. Jesus Christ!
That's for blasphemy.
The quest for the Grail is not archaeology.
It's a race against evil.
If it is captured by the Nazis,
the armies of darkness will march all over the earth.
Do you understand me?
This is an obsession, Dad. I never understood it.
Never.
And neither did Mom.
Oh, yes, she did. Only too well...
...unfortunately.
She kept her illness from me. All I could do was mourn her.
My boy, we're pilgrims in an unholy land.
Frlein Doctor. Where is it?
- How did you get here?  - Where is it?  I want it.
- You came back for the book? Why?  - My father didn't want it incinerated.
Is that what you think of me?  I believe in the Grail, not the swastika.
You count as the enemy of the Grail. Who cares what you think?
You do!
All I have to do is squeeze.
All I have to do is scream.
Got it. Let's get the hell outta here.
- What did you get?   - First available flight out of Germany.
Well, we made it.
When we're airborne, with Germany behind us,
then I'll share that sentiment.
Relax.
Tickets, please.
No ticket!
- Ticket!  - Ticket!
You know, sharing your adventures is an interesting experience.
It's not all we shared.
It's disgraceful. You're old enough to be her... grandfather!
- I'm as human as the next man.  - I was the next man.
Of course... Ships that pass in the night.
Remember the last time we had a quiet drink?
I had a milkshake.
What did we talk about?
We didn't talk.
We never talked.
Do I detect a rebuke?
A regret. It was just the two of us, it was a lonely way to grow up.
If you'd been an ordinary father, you'd have understood that.
- Actually, I was a wonderful father.  - When?
Did I ever tell you to eat up, go to bed, do your homework?  No.
I respected your privacy, and I taught you self-reliance!
You taught me I was less important than people
who'd been dead for 500 years!
I learned it so well, we've hardly spoken for 20 years!
You left just when you were becoming interesting!
- Dad, how can...?  - Very well. I'm here now.
What do you want to talk about?
- I can't think of anything.  - Then why are you complaining?
We have work to do.
When we get to Alexandretta, we will face three challenges.
First: "The Breath of God.
"Only the penitent man will pass."
Second: "The Word of God. Only in the footsteps of God will he proceed."
Third: "The Path of God.
"Only in the leap from the lion's head will he prove his worth."
What does that mean?
I don't know. We'll find out!
We're turning around. They're taking us back to Germany.
I thought it'd take them longer to figure out the radio was dead. Move!
Come on, Dad! Come on!
- I didn't know you could fly a plane.  - Fly, yes...
...land, no.
You're gonna have to use the machine gun. Get it ready!
Eleven o'clock! Dad, eleven o'clock!
What happens at eleven o'clock?
Twelve, eleven, ten... Eleven o'clock, fire!
Dad, are we hit?
More or less.
Son, I'm sorry. They got us.
Hang on, Dad, we're going in!
- Nice landing.  - Thanks.
- Those people are trying to kill us.  - I know, Dad!
- It's a new experience for me.  - It happens to me all the time.
This is intolerable!
This could be close.
Faster, boy, faster!
They don't come any closer than that!
Dad!
He's coming back.
I suddenly remembered my Charlemagne.
"Let my armies be the rocks and the trees and the birds in the sky."
These pages are taken from Professor Jones'diary,
and they include a map pinpointing the location of the Grail.
The Grail is all but in our hands.
However, we would not cross your soil without permission,
nor remove the Grail from your borders without compensation.
What have you brought?
Precious valuables, your Highness,
donated by some of the finest families in all of Germany...
Rolls-Royce Phantom II...
4.3-litre, 30-horsepower, 6-cylinder engine,
with Stromberg down-draught carburettor.
Can go from 0-100 kph in 12.5 seconds.
And I even like the colour.
The keys are in the ignition, your Highness.
You shall have camels, horses, an armed escort,
provisions, desert vehicles and tanks.
You're welcome.
No time to lose. Indiana Jones and his father have escaped.
We go this way. Get that camel out of the way.
What happened to Marcus?
They set out across the desert this afternoon. They took him with them.
Now they have the map!
In this race, there's no silver medal for finishing second.
- Care to wet your whistle, Marcus?  - I'd rather spit in your face.
But as I haven't got any spit...
Must be within three or four miles. Otherwise we're off the map.
Marcus, we're on the brink of the recovery
of the greatest artefact in the history of mankind.
You're meddling with powers you cannot possibly comprehend.
I see Brody. He seems OK.
They've got a tank.
A six-pound gun.
- What are you doing?  Get down!  - Dad, we're well out of range.
- That car was my brother-in-law's.  - Come on!
- I can't see anyone up there.  - Maybe it wasn't Jones.
No. It was him, all right. He's here somewhere.
Put Brody in the tank.
In this sun, without transportation, they're as good as dead.
It's Jones, all right.
Who are they?
Who cares, as long as they keep Donovan busy?
Dad, stay here while we organise some transportation.
- I'll get the horses.  - I'll take the camels.
I don't need camels. No camels!
Who is he?
A messenger from God.
For the unrighteous, the Cup of Life holds everlasting damnation.
Marcus.
"That genius of the Restoration..."
"...aid our own resuscitation."
- Henry!  What are you doing here?  - It's a rescue.
Search him.
What is this book, that miserable little diary of yours?
The book is useless, yet you come back to Berlin to get it. Why?
What are you hiding?
What does the diary tell you that it doesn't tell us?
It tells me that goose-stepping morons like yourself
should try reading books instead of burning them!
Colonel! Jones is getting away!
I think not, Herr Donovan.
Not that Jones, the other Jones!
Sallah, I said no camels, that's five camels!  Can't you count?
Compensation for the car. Your father and Brody...
- Where's my father?  - In the belly of that steel beast.
Dad!
Dad!  Dad!
Junior! Junior!
Junior!
Dad!
Dad!  Get out!
- Henry, the pen.  - What?
The pen is mightier than the sword.
- Look what you did!  - It's war!
Didn't I tell you it was a rescue?
Dad!
- You call this archaeology?  - Get out of there!
How does one get off this thing?
Where's Marcus?
Hang on, Dad!
- Father of Indy, give me your hand!  - Sallah, get Dad!
Give me your hand!
Junior!
Indy!
Oh, God.
I've lost him.
And I never told him anything.
I just wasn't ready, Marcus.
Five minutes would have been enough.
I thought I'd lost you, boy!
I thought you had, too, sir.
Well...
Well done. Come on.
Let's go, then!
Why are you sitting there resting when we're so near the end?  Let's go!
The Canyon of the Crescent Moon.
Helmut, another volunteer!
- I never expected to see you again.  - Like a bad penny, I always turn up.
Step back now, Dr Schneider. Give Dr Jones some room.
He's going to recover the Grail for us.
Impossible?  What do you say?  Ready to go down in history?
As what?  A Nazi stooge, like you?
The Nazis? Is that the limit of your vision?
The Nazis want to write themselves into the Grail legend,
take on the world.
They're welcome.
But I want the Grail itself.
The cup that gives everlasting life.
Hitler can have the world, but he can't take it with him.
I'll be drinking my own health when he's gone the way of the dodo.
The Grail is mine. And you're going to get it for me.
Shooting me won't get you anywhere.
You know something?  You're absolutely right.
Dad!
- Dad!  - Junior.
- No. - Get back!
You can't save him when you're dead. The Grail is all that can save him.
It's time to ask yourself what you believe.
"The Breath of God.
Only the penitent man will pass."
The penitent man will pass.
Penitent man will pass.
Penitent man...
"Only the penitent man will pass."
The penitent man will pass. Penitent? Penitent man?
Penitent man... penitent...
The penitent man is humble before God.
Penitent... penitent...
Penitent man...?
The penitent man is humble...
...kneels before God. Kneel!
I'm through!
We're through.
- He's all right!  - No...
The second challenge is the Word of God.
"Only in the footsteps of God will he proceed."
The Word of God?
Word of...?
Proceed in the footsteps of the Word...
- The Word of God!  - No, Henry, try not to talk.
The name of God.
Jehovah.
But in the Latin alphabet, Jehovah begins with an "l".
J...
Oh, dear.
Idiot!
In Latin, Jehovah starts with an "l".
I...
E...
The Path of God.
"Only in the leap from the lion's head will he prove his worth."
lmpossible. Nobody can jump this.
Indy!  You must hurry!
Come quickly!
It's a leap of faith.
You must believe, boy!  You must... believe.
I knew you'd come.
But my strength has left me.
Who are you?
The last of three brothers who swore an oath
to find the Grail and to guard it.
That was seven hundred years ago.
A long time to wait.
You're strangely dressed for a knight.
I was chosen because I was the bravest and most worthy.
The honour was mine until another came
to challenge me to single combat.
I pass it to you...
...who vanquished me.
I don't have time to explain, but...
Which one is it?
You must choose.
But choose wisely.
For as the true Grail will bring you life,
the false Grail will take it from you.
I'm not a historian.
I have no idea what it looks like.
Which one is it?
Let me choose.
Thank you, Doctor.
Oh, yes.
It's more beautiful than I ever imagined.
This certainly is the Cup of the King of Kings.
Eternal life.
What is happening to me?
What is happening?
He chose...
...poorly.
It would not be made out of gold.
That's the cup of a carpenter.
There's only one way to find out.
You have chosen wisely.
But the Grail cannot pass beyond the Great Seal.
That is the boundary and the price of immortality.
Drop your guns... please!
Dad, get to your feet.
We have got it. Come on!
Elsa, don't move!
- It's ours, Indy. Yours and mine.  - Don't cross the seal.
The knight warned us not to take the Grail from here.
Junior!  Junior!
Elsa...
Don't, Elsa.
Give me your other hand. I can't hold you.
I can reach it. I can reach it.
Give me your other hand!
Elsa!
Junior, give me your other hand. I can't hold on.
I can get it. I can almost reach it, Dad.
Indiana?
Indiana...
Let it go.
Dad.
Please, Dad.
Elsa never really believed in the Grail. She thought she'd found a prize.
What did you find, Dad?
Me?
Illumination.
- And what did you find, Junior?  - "Junior"? Dad...
What does it mean, this "Junior"?
That's his name: Henry Jones Junior.
- I like "Indiana". - We named the dog "Indiana"!
May we go home now, please?
The dog? You are named after the dog?
I've got a lot of fond memories of that dog.
- Ready?  - Ready.
Indy, Henry, follow me!  I know the way!
Got lost in his own museum, huh?
After you, Junior.
Yes, sir.